Finding Aid for Douglass family (Detroit and Ann Arbor, Mich.) papers, 1812-1911
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Douglass family (Detroit and Ann Arbor, Mich.) papers 1812-1911 1837-1900
Douglass family.
851266 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Papers of Benjamin Douglass and his sons, Samuel T. Douglass, Detroit attorney and jurist, and Silas H. Douglas, professor of chemistry at the University of Michigan, and member of Douglass Houghton's Northern Michigan survey. Correspondence, scrapbooks, letter books, and miscellanea concerning family affairs, business and university activities; also contains records of the Douglass and Walker and Campbell Law Firm; and papers of individual members of Silas Douglas’ family, including his wife Helen Welles Douglas, their children Samuel T. Douglas, Marie Louise Douglas, and Catherine Hulbert Douglas, and other Douglas and Welles family members; and photographs.
9 linear feet
1 oversize folders
3 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection came from different sources. Marie Louise Douglas (donor no. 183 ) began donating family papers in 1937. In 1938, she donated the field notes of Silas Douglas from the 1839-40 Douglass Houghton survey. The papers of Samuel T. Douglass came from the U-M library (donor no. 1278 ). Some of the papers of Samuel T. Douglas were donated by Mrs. E. D. Campbell (donor no. 2916 ) in 1952.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Silas H. Douglas (he originally spelled his name Douglass) taught at the University of Michigan from 1844 to 1877. Born in New York state in 1816, he was educated at the Fredonia Academy and at the University of Vermont. He came to Michigan in 1838 and settled in Detroit. He began the study of medicine in the office of Dr. Zina Pitcher, later studying for one term in the Medical Department of the University of Maryland. Douglas accompanied Douglass Houghton on his geological surveys of Michigan in the 1830s. In 1843, he moved to Ann Arbor and began the practice of medicine. A year later he was appointed assistant to Houghton at the U-M and had charge of the work of chemistry during Houghton's absence in the field. After Houghton's death in 1845, Douglas continued in charge of the department and for the remainder of his career worked under different titles in the fields of chemistry, mineralogy, geology, and related subjects. Douglas was largely responsible for the creation of a Chemical Laboratory at the University. This facility was completed and opened for students' work in 1856. Silas Douglas was also founder and officer with the Ann Arbor Gas Company. He died August 26, 1890.
Samuel T. Douglass was an attorney and judge. While serving as judge of the Wayne County circuit court, he became (under the terms of the 1850 state constitution) one of the judges of the Supreme Court. He served here from 1851 to 1857 when he resigned to reenter private practice. Douglass also served several terms on the Detroit Board of Education and was president for one year of the Detroit Young Men's Society.
Silas' son Samuel T. Douglas was a graduate of the University of Michigan and an attorney. When admitted to practice in 1879, he became a member of his uncle's firm (with the name now changed) of Douglas, Bowen & Douglas. The firm had several subsequent name changes with retirements and partner additions. Near the end of his career, the firm name was Douglas, Barbour & Wing. Douglas was long connected with the Washtenaw Gas Company and also served as a director of the Detroit & Security Trust Company.
The Douglass Family collection spans the period 1812-1911 and comprises eight linear feet of manuscripts, one linear ft. of photographs, three outsize volumes, and 1 folder of oversize materials. The collection include the papers of Benjamin Douglass and his two sons, Samuel T. (1814-98) a lawyer and Detroit judge, and Silas H. (1816-90), a professor at The University of Michigan. Although Silas came to use the family name of Douglas rather than Douglass, the paper indicate that there was little consistency.
The collection consists of personal and professional correspondence, letterpress books, business and legal papers, scrapbooks, photographs, and family materials. The collection, except for series of photographs and maps, is arranged by family member name.
Subjects:
Detroit (Mich.). Board of Water Commissioners.; Douglas family.; Flat River (Mich.); Grosse Ile (Mich.); Houghton, Douglass, 1809-1845.; Lawyers--Michigan--Detroit.; Michigan Central Railroad Company.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. President.; Welles family.; University of Michigan. Chemical Laboratory.; Ann Arbor Gas Company.; Douglas, Samuel Townsend, 1853-1932.; Douglas, Marie Louise.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.). Class of 1874.; Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Douglas family.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Interiors.
Contributors:
Campbell, James V. (James Valentine), 1823-1890.; Crapo, Henry Howland, 1804-1869.; Douglas, Silas H. (Silas Hamilton), 1816-1890.; Douglass, Benjamin.; Douglass, Samuel Townsend, 1814-1898.; Duffield, George, 1794-1868.; Kearsley, Jonathan, 1786-1859.; Pitcher, Zina, 1797-1872.; Sager, Abram, 1810-1877.; Sibley, Joseph.; Tappan, Henry Philip, 1805-1881.; Walker, Edward Carey, 1820-1894.; Walker, Henry N. (Henry Nelson), 1811-1886.; Williams, George Palmer, 1802-1881.; Douglas, Samuel Townsend, 1853-1932.; Douglas, Marie Louise.
Maps
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Maps.; East Saginaw (Saginaw, Mich.)--Maps.; Emerson's Addition (Saginaw, Mich.)--Maps.; Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich)--Maps.; Huron, Lake, Region (Mich. and Ont.)--Maps.; Marquette County (Mich.)--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Maps.; Real property--Michigan--Saginaw--Maps.
Maps: Contributors
Houghton, Douglass, 1809-1845.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Ambrotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Drawings.; Scrapbooks.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Benjamin Douglass Papers
  Much of the Benjamin Douglass correspondence is of a personal nature with Lucy Townson Douglass.
  - Correspondence 1812, 1815-1847, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Genealogical notes (Box 1)
- Silas Douglas papers
  The Silas Douglas series consists of correspondence and subject files dealing with family affairs, business matters and, in large part, with his career at the University of Michigan. Of special note is his copy of Douglass Houghton's field notes from his geological survey of the Upper Peninsula and records of the Ann Arbor Gas Company which Douglas founded.
  - Correspondence
    - 1837-1888, 45 folders (Box 1)
      (some gaps in dates)
  - Other materials
    - Resolutions on the death of Silas H. Douglas 1890 (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning diploma fees at the University of Michigan 1860 (Box 2)
    - Subscriptions for addition to the medical building 1864 (Box 2)
    - Report of Douglas' faculty activities 1875-1877 (Box 2)
    - Certificate to teach and appointment as assistant professor of chemistry signed by Douglass Houghton (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning St. Andrews Episcopal Church, in Ann Arbor 1878-1887 (Box 2)
    - Tax receipts 1848-1898 (Box 2)
    - Records with the Chemical Laboratory at the University of Michigan 1870-1873 (Box 2)
    - Specifications for residence on Washington St. undated (Box 2)
    - Douglass Houghton field notes from Upper Peninsula geological survey 1839-1840, 2 folders original and typescript copy (Box 2)
      (Silas Douglas' copy made 1862 ?)
    - Inventory of books belonging to the Estate of Douglass Houghton (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning the case of the Regents of the University of Michigan vs. Douglas and Rose 1876-1878 (Box 2)
    - Receipts and business papers of Silas Douglas (Box 2)
    - Papers concerning the Sarah A. Byrne account 1877-1888 (Box 2)
    - Invoice of furniture 1847 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Gas Co.
      - Annual reports 1870-1885 (Box 2)
      - Contracts and other legal materials (Box 2)
      - Cashbooks 1858-1887, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 2)
      - Ledger 1859-1874 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1857-1861 (Volume 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1866-1879 (Box 2)
  - Letterbooks
    - 1866-1867 (Box 3)
    - 1867-1869 (Box 3)
    - 1870-1874 (Box 3)
    - 1874-1880 (Box 3)
    - 1881-1885 1887 (Box 3)
    - 1885-1888 (Box 3)
  - Recipe and note book 1838-1841 (Box 3)
  - Account book 1846-1866 (Box 3)
  - Ledger 1867-1881 (Box 3)
  - Account book 1864-1873 (Box 3)
  - Index to journal undated (Box 3)
- Helen Welles Douglas
  The Helen Welles Douglas papers consists of correspondence received, mainly from her parents John and Sarah Welles
  - Correspondence
    - 1840s Undated (Box 4)
    - 1854-1857 (from parents John and Sarah Welles) (Box 4)
    - 1862-1880 (Box 4)
- Douglas family
  There is a separate series of papers for the children of Silas and Helen Welles Douglas: Alice Helen Douglas, Marie Louise Douglas, Lily C. Douglas, Sarah Douglas, and Catherine (Kate) Hulbert Douglas, and Samuel T. Douglas, an 1873 graduate of the University of Michigan who practiced with his uncle Samuel T. Douglass' law firm in Detroit.
  - Alice Douglas correspondence 1881-1910 (Box 4)
  - Marie Louise Douglas
    - Correspondence
      - Undated, 4 folders (Box 4)
      - 1876-1880 (Box 4)
      - 1881 (Box 4)
      - 1882-1883 (Box 4)
      - 1884-1887 (Box 4)
      - 1888-1891 (Box 4)
      - 1892-1909 (Box 4)
      - June-July 1911 (Box 4)
      - August 1911 (Box 4)
      - September 1911 (Box 4)
    - Letters from Lois Angell McLaughlin to Marie Louise Douglass 1881-1886 (Box 4)
    - Reminiscences and articles on the Douglass family (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous papers (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook 1865-1917 (Box 4)
  - Catherine Hulbert Douglas
    - Correspondence
      - Undated (Box 4)
      - 1856-1867 (Box 4)
      - 1875-1886 (Box 4)
      - 1895-1896 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1860s-1920s (Volume 2)
  - Samuel T. Douglas [son of Silas]
    - Papers 1875-1917 (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook, 1872-1873 (Box 4)
    - Class notes for U-M class in rhetoric (Box 4)
  - Henry W. Douglas [son of Silas] papers 1890, 1917 (Box 4)
  - William Douglas [son of Silas] papers 1876-1887 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous family correspondence 1868-1906 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous family essays (Box 4)
- Samuel T. Douglass [brother of Silas]
  The papers of Samuel T. Douglass consist of correspondence and other materials relating to his legal business in Detroit, but with some items about politics, his farm, and family affairs. Associated with his papers are letterbooks, record books, and other materials of the Douglass and Walker Law Firm
  - Correspondence 1833-1897, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Legal and business papers
    - 1833-1849 (Box 5)
    - 1850-1855 (Box 5)
    - 1855-1859 (Box 5)
    - 1860-1864 (Box 5)
    - 1865-1869 (Box 5)
    - 1870-1889 (Box 5)
    - 1890-1898 and estate papers (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1874-1878 (Box 5)
  - Douglass and Walker Law Firm
    - Letterbooks
      - 1837-1839 (Box 5)
      - 1839-1840 (Box 5)
      - 1841 (Box 5)
      - 1842-1843 (Box 5)
      - 1847-1850 (Volume 3)
    - Record of evidence in cases tried, 2 volumes (Box 5)
    - Chancery register 1838-1845 (Box 6)
    - Records concerning the Beaudien Case 1865 (Box 6)
    - Legal Record Books, unidentified, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - Ledger 1840-1850 (Box 6)
    - Ledger 1845-1850 (Box 6)
    - Law Register 1848-1858 (Box 6)
    - Day Book 1843-1850 (Box 6)
- Welles Family Papers
  There is also a small Welles Family series containing correspondence and business papers of Helen Welles Douglas parents, John and Sarah Welles. This includes some papers of Henry W. Welles who served some times as treasurer of the University of Michigan. Records of John A. Welles relate to his land holdings, business dealings, and to his estate following his death.
  - Henry W. Welles (U-M treasurer)
    - Miscellaneous papers of Henry W. Welles, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Cash book 1863-1864 (Box 7)
  - John A. Welles
    - Cash journal/cash ledger, Emerson addition, pages from 1864-1865 (Box 7)
    - La Fontaine Farm land books circa 1855-1867, 5 volumes (Box 7)
    - Journal 1859-1865 (Box 7)
    - Ledger 1859-1864 (Box 7)
    - Daybooks 1865-1871, 2 volumes (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers of John A. Welles and the Welles estate, 7 folders; 3 volumes (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Genealogy research, 3 volumes (Box 8)
    (also in oversize folder Ac)
  - Miscellaneous autograph books, accounts, diary of unspecified family members, 8 volumes (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Photos of the home and family of Silas H. Douglas (Box 9)
  - Albums of family and acquaintances (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous daguerreotypes and tintypes of family members. (Box 9)
- Maps
  - Map of Saginaw Bay and eastern Michigan shore from Clinton River to Middle Island, by Silas H. Douglas 1838 (Box 9)
  - Map of Lake Huron shore from Au Sable Point to Sturgeon Point 1838, photostatic copy (Folder 1)
  - Map of Lake Superior shore from Chocolay River to Granite Pont, copied from original by Douglass Houghton, photostatic copy (Folder 1)
  - Map of block bounded by Division, Huron, State, and Washington Streets, Ann Arbor, Mich. undated (Folder 1)
  - Printed map of Forest Hill Cemetery, Ann Arbor, Mich. 1858 (Folder 1)
  - Printed map of Emerson's to East Saginaw 1865, 3 copies (Folder 1)
  - Printed map of Emerson's Addition 1860s (Folder 1)